Guide to the Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh Records, 1955-2018 AIS.1977.22
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh Records
1955-2018
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Gaelic Arts Society (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1977.22
1.7 Linear Feet (1 records center box, 1 microfilm reel)
This collection contains the records of the Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh from the period of 1955 to 2018. It includes a wide array of materials related to the business of the society's Board of Governors, events and programs hosted or sponsored by the society, its finances, membership records, newsletters, and correspondences, as well as materials related to other cultural organizations and institutions.
History
Rev. Brother Dominic Reardon C.S.Sp., a member of Duquesne University's administrative staff and native of Dublin, Ireland, founded the Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh in 1955, in response to an enquiry from the Women's Intercultural Group of the Oakland YMCA for someone able to write a prayer and menu in Irish-Gaelic. The society's goal is the promotion of the rich legacy of the history, literature, traditions, and crafts of the Irish people to all Western Pennsylvanians with an interest in Irish culture, with its membership not limited solely to Irish Americans or native Irish. It aims further to promote a consciousness of the influences of Irish thought and action on the advancement of American ideals.
Throughout its history, the society has been deeply involved within the Pittsburgh Irish community, holding various events including lectures on various aspects of Irish culture, banquets, St. Patrick's Day parades, as well as promoting the events of other organizations such as the Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theater and the Pittsburgh Irish Festival. Their banquets and programs on Irish culture have hosted eminent Irish historians as well as former Irish ambassadors and diplomats. In 1963, Rev. Brother Reardon and several other members of the society were received by the third President of the Republic of Ireland, Éamon de Valera, at Áras an Uachtarain in Dublin, as part of the society's annual "Tour to Ireland".
During the 1970's and early 1980's, the society sponsored and organized the "Pittsburgh Irish Fortnight", a program of Irish cultural lectures and events, in conjunction with the University of Pittsburgh and the Irish American Cultural Institute, a cultural organization directly affiliated with the President of Ireland. In addition to a concert presented by the Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann, the Irish Fortnight hosted annually noted Irish artists, academics, and politicians as guest speakers.
Notable society members have included 37th Governor of Pennsylvania, David L. Lawrence, Henry X. O'Brien, a Justice of the Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, and James W. Knox, former Allegheny County controller. The society held a peak membership of approximately 530 members by 1990. Despite a decline in membership, the society continues to function into the present day, organizing educational and celebratory functions related to Ireland as well as publishing a monthly newsletter, The Gazette. Its cultural programs have similarly come to encompass selective topics in the culture of the "Celtic nations" in general, including that of Scotland, Wales, Brittany, and the Isle of Man.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the records of the Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh from the period of 1955 to 2018. Its contents are generally related to the society's promotion of Irish culture through various programs and events, as well as the history of the society itself and its routine business.
It includes a wide array of materials related to the business of the society's Board of Governors, events and programs hosted or sponsored by the society and its finances, membership records, newsletters, and correspondences, as well as materials related to other cultural organizations and institutions. The collection also contains a digitized copy of the society's scrapbook, within which are materials related to the society's activities and members from the late 1950's to the late 1970's.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into nine series:
Series I. Board of Governors, 1955-2018
Series II. Events & Programs, 1960-2017
Series III. Financial, 1957-2018
Series IV. Membership Records, 1962-2017
Series V. Newsletters, The Gazette, 2005-2018
Series VI. Other Organizations, 2002-2015
Series VII. Topical Folders, 1960-2018
Series VIII. Realia, undated
Series IX. Scrapbook, 1959-1977
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The scrapbook was originally microfilmed by the Archives of Industrial Society from originals in possession of the Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh, June 1977.
Additional records were donated by The Gaelic Arts Society, through their President, Wilma Gaughan in 2018.
Existence and Location of Originals
Original scrapbook retained by The Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh.
Previous Citation
Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh Records, AIS.1977.22, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Additional collections at the Archives Service Center pertaining to local Irish-American organizations include:
Irish Centre of Pittsburgh Records, AIS.1977.25, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Daughters of Erin Court #9 Records, AIS.1977.31, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scrapbooks; Arts -- Pennsylvania; Art and popular culture -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Irish -- Pennsylvania; Irish -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Arts -- Pennsylvania -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Societies and clubs; Programs (Documents); Ethnic groups; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Events -- Irish Fortnight; Societies; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Events -- St. Patrick's Day; Pennsylvania -- Events -- Irish festival; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Events -- Irish festival; Societies -- Ireland and Northern Ireland; Arts -- Pennsylvania -- Societies -- Irish; Arts -- Pennsylvania -- Societies -- Celtic; Arts -- Pennsylvania -- Societies -- Gaelic; Knox, James W., 1919-2001; Gaelic Arts Society (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Board of Governors, 1955-2018; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains primarily the minutes of the society's Board of Governors' monthly meetings during the years 1960 to 2018 (with significant gaps in between), several of the Board's correspondences, election returns for the year 1964, and a list of its members and officers during the period of 1955 to 1990.
  - Correspondence, 1964-2016 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Election Returns, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of Officers and Members, 1955-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 2018 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rosters, 2000-2013 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Events & Programs, 1960-2017; II.
  This series contains programs, committee reports, fliers, and brochures pertaining to some of the events sponsored by the society from 1960 to 2017. These events range from various celebratory functions honoring St. Patrick to guest lectures on both Irish and broadly Celtic culture.
  - An Evening of Fellowship with the Gaels, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 40th Anniversary Mass, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 60th Anniversary Banquet ("Honoring St. Patrick"), 2016 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Annual Luncheon, 1960-2014 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Annual Meeting, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Presentation on Brittany, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Christmas Party, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Event Calendar, 2016-2017 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fashion Show, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Generic Funeral Home Memorial, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - High Tea, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - History - Notecards from a Presentation, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Irish Theatre & the Abbey Theatre, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Irish-Gaelic Poetry (Program), undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "An Irish Wake", 2016 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Isle of Manx, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Knox, James W. (in honor of), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Luncheon Lists, 2001-2015 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Memorial Mass and Service for Deceased Members, 2014-2017 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Miller, Kathleen Marie Rooney (1955-1987) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Moya Brennan ("The Voice of Clannad"), 2017 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Notifications of Events and Meetings, c. 2001-2016 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Pittsburgh Irish Festival, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Poetry of Ireland, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Program Committee, 1961-2015 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Program Schedule, 1995-2008 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Program Suggestions, c. 2016 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Sketches of Ireland (Organ and Vocal Music), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Speakers, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - St. Patrick (notes on), c. 2008 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - St. Patrick's Day Banquet/Dinner, 1974-2006 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Alan Stanford, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Tartan Day, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Tour to Ireland, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Financial, 1957-2018; III.
  This series contains documents related to the society's routine finances including various notes, correspondences, treasurer's reports, balances, expense reports, and budgets from the period of 1957 to 2018, with significant gaps in this timeline.
  - Budget Planning, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Estate of Margaret E. Maloney, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Financial Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Financial Correspondence, 2000-2016 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Membership Subscriptions/Dues, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Financial Notes, c. 1963-2017 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Proposed Budgets, 2013-2015 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Financial Statements, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Income and Expense Reports, 2015-2018 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 2013-2015 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Membership Records, 1962-2017; IV.
  This series contains membership rosters, brochures, and application materials as well as obituaries for certain past members, including former society president, Earl McCabe.
  - History, Constitution & Roster (Booklets), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Membership Applications and Due Notices (Blank), c. 2002 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Membership Brochures, c. 2014 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Membership Changes, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - New Members List, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Membership Roster Notebooks, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Membership Rosters, 2004-2012 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Obituary, Earl McCabe, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Obituary, Elizabeth Woodland, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Newsletters, The Gazette, 2005-2018; V.
  This series contains issues of the society's monthly newsletter from the period of 2005 to 2018, The Gazette. The newsletter contains messages from the society's president to its membership, program schedules, as well as articles on various topics related to Irish history and culture.
  - The Gazette, 2005-2010 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - The Gazette, 2011-2015 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - The Gazette, 2016-2018 (Box 1, Folder 82)
- Other Organizations, 2002-2015; VI.
  This series contains the brochures, financial correspondences, and publications of various organizations either sponsored by the society or centered around topics related to Irish or Celtic culture in general.
  - Community College of Allegheny County, Course, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - The Corrymeela Community, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Irish American Archives Society of Cleveland and Northeast Ohio, 2014-2015 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - St. David's Society of Pittsburgh, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Nationality Rooms Program, c. 2007-2011 (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Topical Folders, 1960-2018; VII.
  This series consists of topical folders which contain society correspondences (the bulk of which originate from various society presidents), business-related materials, graphic designs for varied uses, several undated photographs, and two CD's containing a 2015 recording of the WEDO radio show "Echoes of Erin". Other folders contain narrative texts, sheet music, and fact sheets related to Irish culture.
  - Basic Facts About Ireland and Northern Ireland, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Business Cards, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Bylaws Revisions, c. 2016 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Correspondence, 1996-2018 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Correspondence to Members from President, 1990-2010 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - "Echoes of Erin" Radio Show, (Audio Discs), September 6, 2015; 2 cds (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Insurance, 2001-2016 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Inventory of Equipment, 2004-2017 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Letterhead (Blank), c. 2005 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Logo Designs, undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Narrative Texts - (Jokes), undated (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Presidential Medallion, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Sheet Music, undated (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Web Page Designs, undated (Box 1, Folder 102)
- Realia, undated; VIII.; 3 items
  This series contains three medallions suspended by white ribbon, illustrated with a clover leaf, campfire, and crozier, and emblazoned with the word "TARA". These medals were most likely presented to recipients of the Tara Award, honoring certain members of the Daughters of Erin, Court #9, the women's auxiliary of the Knights of Equity, an Irish Catholic Fraternal organization.
  - "Tara" Medallion, undated (Box 1, Item 1)
  - "Tara" Medallion, undated (Box 1, Item 2)
  - "Tara" Medallion, undated (Box 1, Item 3)
- Scrapbook, 1959-1977; IX.; 1 microfilm_reel (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
  This scrapbook contains photographs, newspaper clippings, correspondences, pamphlets and brochures pertaining to the Gaelic Arts Society of Pittsburgh's events and members from 1959 to 1977. A significant portion of the newspaper clippings within the scrapbook relate to profiles of the society by the press as well as Don McNamara's "The Irish in Pittsburgh" newspaper column. Programs represented within the scrapbook include the society's various Tours to Ireland, St. Patrick Day Parades, banquets, the 1968 "An Evening of Irish Fashions" show, the 1974 to 1977 occurrences of the "Pittsburgh Irish Fortnight", 1975 Memorial Mass for third President of the Republic of Ireland, Éamon de Valera, as well as other speaking events organized by the society, including those hosting several diplomats and ambassadors of the Republic of Ireland. It further includes a transcript of a speech given by former Minister for Foreign Affairs for the Republic of Ireland and Teachta Dála, Dr. Garret Fitzgerald on October 1, 1975 regarding the connection between Ireland and America as well as the contemporary conflict in Northern Ireland. Other materials include a citation from the Pennsylvania House of Representatives congratulating the society's founder, Rev. Brother Dominic Reardon C.S.Sp, for being named 1976's "Man of the Year" by the Irish American Cultural Society of Bucks County, and related correspondences, photographs, and newspaper clippings.